Today's דף daf is ה, He, five. We pick up in the
middle of ד Dalet עמוד ב. Amud Bet. We're dealing with the
fact that in the משנה, Mishnah, רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, even when
you pay a full שקל shekel for you and somebody else, רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir insists on two קולבונות, kolbonot, two types of fees.
So the גמרא Gemara basically says that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is
of the position that even somebody who pays a straight half שקל
shekel pays a fee. And it's based on this idea that the
שקל shekel of אש eish that God showed משה, Moshe, the half
שקל, shekel, presumably it has to be totally pure. So every real-world,
non-Platonic half שקל shekel is a little bit less perfect, and therefore
you need this thing to round.
And so that's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So now the גמרא Gemara
continues on the two dots. There's a little א Aleph in parentheses,
in curved parentheses, about two-fifths of the way down. כזה, Kaze, and
then there's two dots. Now we go to the next line of
the משנה. Mishnah.
נתן סלע ונטל שקל. Natan sela ve’notal shekel. You gave a סלע
sela and you got back a שקל. shekel. Again, it's confusing because
a סלע sela in the משנה Mishnah is a biblical שקל shekel
and a שקל shekel in the משנה Mishnah is a half שקל.
shekel. Effectively, you gave a שקל, shekel, you got back a half
שקל. shekel. The משנה Mishnah says חייב שני קולבונות. chayav sheni kolbonot.
You have to pay the two קולבונות, kolbonot, two of these fees.
Now why is that? You would think that's your normal transaction. You
give a whole, you get back a half, you get back the
change. Maybe that should only be one fee. So why does the
משנה Mishnah have you paying two fees? אמר רבי אלעזר רבי מאיר
היא. Amar Rabbi Elazar Rabbi Meir hee. Rabbi Elazar said that line
of the משנה Mishnah goes according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Now
I should mention that in the תוספתא, Tosefta, actually it explicitly says
דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. So while it sounds a little
bit shocking, here's a position of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, then the
סתם משנה Stam Mishnah continues and it sounds like it's the חכמים,
Chachamim, and he says, no, no, no, that line is still רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir. That actually is how it's identified in the תוספתא.
Tosefta. So remember, according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, even a straight
half שקל shekel you pay a fee. So if you do two
things, you both do an exchange—you give a whole and you get
back a half—so that's one fee, and then you get your straight
fee for just giving the half. So therefore he says this idea
that you give two fees when you give a whole, get back
a half is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. One of the fees for
the rounding and one of the fees for the exchange. דתניא, De'tanya,
we’ll skip the parentheses. We taught in a
ברייתא. Baita. אלו חייבין בקולבון, Elu chayavin be'kolbon, etc. He basically quotes
our משנה. Mishnah. דתניא, De'tanya, דתנן. de'tnan. Anyway, המפסיע
חייב בקולבון, hamapseeah chayav be'kolbon, and he gives the case of if
you pay for two people it's one קולבון, kolbon, קולבון אחד. kolbon
echad. רבי מאיר אומר שני קולבונות. Rabbi Meir omer sheni kolbonot. Rabbi
Meir says that it's two קולבונות. kolbonot. Now how does that prove
that it's רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, other than making the point that
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you always give a קולבון kolbon even
for a straight half שקל? shekel? So for a whole שקל shekel
you give two קולבונות. kolbonot. And therefore for a whole שקל shekel
you get back a half, you give two: one again for the
one you always give and one for the exchange. It also could
be the reason it says דתניא, de'tanya, even though it seems to
be quoting the משנה, Mishnah, is for the reason I said: that
in the תוספתא Tosefta that line in the משנה Mishnah ends with
saying that when you give a whole and get back a half
you pay two, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. And sometimes what
you get in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, it happens in the בבלי Bavli
as well, but often in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, is it quotes the
beginning and the proof is really from the end. So it really
could be here that the proof is not just an inference that
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would always have you pay one and therefore
in this case have you pay two, but that actually in the
תוספתא Tosefta it explicitly says that when you give a whole and
get back a half you pay two, דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi
Meir, which is exactly what what's-his-name is saying, what רבי אלעזר Rabbi
Elazar is saying.
Yes, so the why if you have to pay a קולבון kolbon
for the exchange when you get back, that can't be explained in
terms of the Platonic, you know...
No, so there's two reasons. One is a transaction fee. Right, one
is a transaction fee and one is the standard amount you always
pay with every half שקל.
shekel. Right, one is for the impurity, one is the service.
Exactly. So that's what—so we're saying that line is רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. Now ואמר, ve’amar, ומר, u’mar, sometimes in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi it
drops an א, Aleph, like רבי בא Rabbi Ba in the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi is רבי אבא. Rabbi Abba. So often it drops the א.
Aleph. So ומר u’mar means ואמר. ve’amar. אמר רב, Amar Rav, but
רב Rav says, דברי הכל היא. divrei hakol hee. No, that line
that when you get back a half you pay two קולבונות, kolbonot,
everybody agrees to that, even the חכמים. Chachamim. Now why? The חכמים
Chachamim say a straight half שקל shekel you wouldn't pay, so why
are you paying two here? So דאמר רבי מאיר אחד שוקל שהוא
נותן—now De'amar Rabbi Meir echad shokel she'hu noten the problem is that
it's quoting רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and again there's a real problem
here with the text. So anyway let's read it. דאמר רבי מאיר
אחד שוקל שהוא נותן ואחד שוקל שהוא נוטל ואחד דברי תורה. De'amar
Rabbi Meir echad shokel she'hu noten ve'echad shokel she'hu notel ve'echad divrei
Torah. So
basically
it's saying according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, it really skipped what
the חכמים Chachamim would say, but according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
you would actually pay not two in this case, you'd pay three.
Why three? You pay one for just the transaction of giving the
money, you pay one for getting the change, and you pay—they get
you coming and going. Right, it used to be what are the
bridges? They used to only... They were charging in one direction, now
they charge you in both directions. They get you coming and going.
So you get for any transaction you give the whole שקל, shekel,
you pay one, you get back a half, you pay another one,
and every half שקל shekel anyway, not just for the transaction, but
for the fact that you're paying the half שקל shekel is you
give one, and that's אחד הוא דבר תורה, echad hu d'var Torah,
one based on this פסוק pasuk in the תורה Torah based on
what we already said. It's very bizarre because according to that, then
if you give a straight half שקל shekel you should give two,
right? Just the transaction of giving plus the normal one. You know,
so I really can't tell you that I really fully explained the
logic here about when you are giving and when not, you know.
Because so anyway, someone says that according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
you give three in this case, and according to the חכמים chachamim
you do give two. What's the two? If you gave a straight
half you'd give zero, but if you give a whole you're paying
two, one for giving too much and the other so and the
other for getting back. Why that counts as two transactions I gotta
tell ya I don't understand what it's I don't understand. רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar makes a lot more sense to me. Okay and now
the גמרא Gemara continues or maybe it maybe this is like a
duplication of the same
law. על דעתיה דרב ג' קולבונות אינון, Al dateih d'Rav gimel kolbonot
inun, and according to רב, Rav, meaning according to רב Rav according
to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, it would be three קולבונות. kolbonot. אתא
רבי ירמיה רבי שמואל בר רב יצחק בשם רב ג' קולבונות אינון.
Ata Rabbi Yirmeya Rabbi Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak b'shem Rav gimel kolbonot
inun. There are three קולבונות kolbonot again according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. אחד שאתה נותן ואחד שאתה נוטל ואחד
לדבר תורה. Echad she'ata noten v'echad she'ata notel v'echad l'dvar Torah.
Okay, so basically and therefore according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir there'd
be three and according to the חכמים chachamim actually the line that
says two when you give one and get back a half works
because it's one you pay a קולבון kolbon for each side of
the transaction. Again, if that's true, then why according to the חכמים
chachamim every half שקל shekel you shouldn't always pay one, I don't
really understand. So again, I don't think I'm just being stupid here.
I, you know, I looked at the מפרשים, mefarshim, nobody seems to
be able, at least as far as I've been able to see,
to explain it in a way that really I think fully makes
sense of it. But okay. I do want to use this opportunity
to say, you know, this double language, part of it as I
said, with all these parentheses we've just dealt with, part of it
as I said is that the ירושלמי Yerushalmi has a different syntax
than, you know, a style than the בבלי, Bavli, so some things
just seem like, you know, it doesn't have the סתם stam to
create the flow and something seems a little more abrupt. But I
also wanted to make a mention because I because
in my exchange with Professor Seth Schwartz he mentioned to me that
of course you know that the ירושלמי שקלים Yerushalmi Shekalim has been
heavily influenced by the בבלי. Bavli. I said oh really? So apparently
Sussman, who's the big scholar of the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, who was the
one sort of who wrote the introduction to that new I think
they came out with a whole manuscript of כתב יד ליידן, Ksav
Yad Leiden, they redid the whole thing in this one volume, anyway
he wrote the whole introduction to that. He did a study many
years ago, like 30 years ago, I'm trying to track down the
article, where he basically shows that
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi as it's printed in the current text has two
layers to it. The original ירושלמי Yerushalmi layer and a second layer
that was heavily influenced basically, you know, by the בבלי Bavli and
that sort of got integrated with. Not just שקלים? Shekalim? No, specifically
ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. And that one of the reasons for it was that
because when they decided to print שקלים Shekalim in the בבלי, Bavli,
which he also sort of assumes like I was saying is just
for completion, if you're doing all of מועד Moed has a בבלי
Bavli and שקלים Shekalim is the only thing that didn't, so the
printers decided let's include שקלים Shekalim with the ירושלמי Yerushalmi in the
בבלי, Bavli, that in that process somehow, and I don't have the
exact particulars which is why I'm trying to track down the article,
but somehow some other whether it was gloss or version or some
other thing got grafted onto it and created this whole בבלי Bavli
layer that exists in our current ירושלמי שקלים. Yerushalmi Shekalim. And so
when you go to the new edition of the כתב יד ליידן,
Ksav Yad Leiden, of the transcription of the כתב יד ליידן, Ksav
Yad Leiden, it's very clear what the original layer was and what
the added layer is. So some of these things, when the text
seems to duplicate and so on and we'll have a little bit
more of that today, you should be aware that there definitely, you
know, in this text of all the ירושלמי Yerushalmis there's a particular
בבלי Bavli layer of influence. All right, so anyway let's continue now.
האחין והשותפין שחייבין בקולבון, Ha'achin v'hashutafin shechayavin b'kolbon,
yes.
Can you describe somewhat what that layer is?
Well when we come up to sections of it, I'll try to
point it out. Okay, but I but right now I've only read
like a one-sentence summary of it, so I'm trying to get the
article, and when I read the article I'll let you know more.
What was this, you're saying?
Well what we just did, right, though it's not clear there what's
בבליאיק Bavlayik about it, but some of this you know, but it
could just be some of the, but yes, some of this doubling
language that we hear have here could be a part of the
influence of a second version that's been grafted on. But what's particularly
בבליאיק Bavlayik about what we did is not clear, but I'll try
to point out something later today. האחין והשותפין Ha'achin v'hashutafin now you
have brothers
and partners...
partners, but of course we're, I'm going to read this as a
as a hybrid, like אברהם Avraham says, right, גר ותושב אנכי עמכם
ger vetoshav anochi imachem
in this week's פרשה, parsha, there's actually a phrase for this. I'm
sure Rabbi Dove here knows the word, which is the vav that
serves to create a hyphenated word, not two things. גר ותושב Ger
vetoshav means a resident alien. גר תושב אנכי עמכם. Ger toshav anochi
imachem. The vav actually creates a hyphenated word. So, you know the
name for that, how there's a term in biblical Hebrew how the
vav does that. So האחין והשותפין Ha'achin ve'hashutafim means brothers
slash, you know, brother-partners. Okay, so brother-partners, although again רמב"ם Rambam does
read this as two
cases, שחייבין בקולבון ופטורין ממעשר בהמה. she'hayavin b'kalbon u'pturin mi'ma'aser behema. The
brother-partners who are obligated in the קולבון kalbon are exempt from מעשר
בהמה, ma'aser behema, because obligated in the קולבון kalbon means that you're
there as individuals, not as a, not as a corporate entity. So
therefore you are a normal partnership of multiple individuals. So therefore you're
each one is חייב hayyav in a קולבון. kalbon. So if you
give for all of you, you have to pay a קולבון kalbon
for everyone, but you are exempt from מעשר בהמה ma'aser behema because
שותפות, shutafut, partnership, is exempt from מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behema.
So what's a case?
בשחלקו וחזרו ונשתתפו. beshe'hilku ve'hazru venishtatfu. They divided the estate and then
they decided to go back into partnership. So in that case what's,
since they divided the estate, it's everybody's private property that they're now
partnering in. So that's a normal partnership. A normal partnership is חייב
hayyav in a קולבון, kalbon, it sees a collection of individuals here,
and an exemption of
מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behema. שחייבין במעשר בהמה ופטורין מן הקולבון, she'hayavin b'ma'aser
behema u'pturin min ha'kalbon, the reverse, that you're חייב hayyav in מעשר
בהמה ma'aser behema and exempt in the קולבון, kalbon, which means that
you're a corporate entity, is בשלא
חלקו, beshe'lo hilku, you never divided the estate. So that's like the
one case in הלכה halacha where הלכה halacha recognizes this idea of
a corporation as opposed to a partnership, an estate that hasn't been
divided, that exists as an entity and not just as a partnership
of individuals. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, Rabbi Elazar says, והן
שחלקו גדיים כנגד תישים ותישים כנגד גדיים. ve'hen she'hilku gedayim k'neged tyashim
u'tyashim k'neged gedayim. That's only when they sort of divided and reconnected
that they're considered to be a partnership and not an estate is
only when the original division was not down the center, that one
person took the goats and the other person took the תישים tyashim
or rams. What's a
תיש? tyash? Rams? He just translates it kids. גדיים Gedayim are kid
goats. No, תישים tyashim are adult goats. גדיים נגד תישים Gedayim neged
tyashim is the phrase. Okay. So when they split, one person took
kid goats and the other person took the adult goats. תישים כנגד
גדיים, tyashim k'neged gedayim, or the reverse, right, or
whatever. אבל אם חלקו גדיים כנגד גדיים, Aval im hilku gedayim k'neged
gedayim, if we said, you take half these kid goats, I'll take
half. You take half the adult goats, I'll take half. ותישים כנגד
תישים. v'tyashim k'neged tyashim. In that case, so הוא חלקו משעה ראשונה.
hu chelko m'sha'ah rishonah. That is the portion that you always deserved.
This is the famous debate that the בבלי Bavli calls יש ברירה
yesh breira or not. Do we say that when we do a
division, הוברר הדבר, huvra hadavar, retroactively shows that this is always the
portion that you were going to get? So we divide an estate.
If, you know, if I take the house and somebody else takes
the car, we can't say that when we got the estate it
turns out that the house was always mine and the car was
always his. It's like clearly that's a new decision about how to
rearrange the division. But if what we say is that, you know,
that he takes, you know, that this guy takes one
car and I take the other car, the same type of a
car, he just gets one and I get the other, we could
say that that shows that retroactively even when we got the estate,
that was the portion that was always coming to us. So when
it's somehow a type of a split down the middle, we can
imagine that even though the decision was made later, it somehow retroactively
demonstrates that this was always the portion that I was going to
get.
Like a נפקא מינה nafka mina then, though.
Well, here's a נפקא מינה. nafka mina. Okay, so the נפקא מינה
nafka mina the גמרא Gemara imagines here is the following. Now, what
should that matter? Right, now we still divided, and if we still
divided and then we're going to rejoin, it's still going to be
a new
partnership. So the מפרשים mefarshim here say two things. One is that
when you reconstitute, can we say that you're reverting back to the
original estate, or do we view this as a new thing? Okay,
so if basically what we did was the type of division was
clearly, I'll tell you what, I'll swap you, because when we inherit
the estate, we imagine it, I'm fifty percent of the car, I'm
fifty percent of the house, and then we'll say, look, I'll swap
you my portion in the house for your portion in the car.
Clearly there was a transaction that took place to create the division,
and then when we decide to join it together, it's clearly a
new thing, because it's clearly not just like, you know, the estate
pulled apart and came back, there actually was some bartering and exchanging
and transactions. So if we were to rejoin, it would now be
a new thing, it would be a new entity, a new partnership.
But if we basically said, you know, we all inherited, you know,
this I don't know, pile of books here... let's split it down
the middle, you take those books, I take these books, and two
days later we said, you know what, let's get back together again
and join again into partnership and be booksellers, and we put all
of our books back, there, since there was no real
transaction imagined at the initial place, we just took our natural halves,
and then we came back, we could be seen as reconstituting the
old entity.
Now the entity always existed.
It always existed, it was never really like we sort of split
it up as much as like took our natural halves, so we
can somehow reun -- now that's not so obvious. I would say
at the end of the day, once you split you split, how
do you know you can reconstitute? But there's another application of this,
which is not just when we get back together have we created
a new entity or reconstituted the old one. But there's another הלכה
halacha by מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behemah. Not only is an animal owned
by partners exempt from מעשר בהמה, ma'aser behemah, but לקוח lakuach is
exempt from מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behemah. If I go to Charlie here,
and I buy Charlie's a cow, and then the cow gives birth,
so that actually would be exempt because actually there's a question, is
לקוח lakuach פטור patur in the first generation or the second generation?
I don't want to get into all that. But at some level,
if I buy something from Charlie and it's not my original animal,
I'm exempt from מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah because it's purchased. So here's
a more obvious נפקא מינה. nafkamina. If we split the estate, and
he takes half the animals and I take half, if we see
that as just we're taking the part that naturally was coming to
us, there was no transaction, so those animals would be חייב chayav
in מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behemah. If, however, we said here, I'll give
you these animals and I'll take the car, so then half of
the animals Charlie's got are לקוח lakuach and therefore because he
bought them in exchange for his portion somewhere else. And therefore it's
exempt from מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah if you view it as a
transaction and לקוח lakuach rather than as a natural split of the
estate.
Why is the word ברירה breira to conceptualize that? Well, that's always
caught me -- that's where he got me.
So you know, here it could be right, so in this case
of the estate you don't have to say it's like הוברר לכתחילה
huvrar l'chatchila that when the guy died, that this was your portion,
you could just sort of say that, you know, that it's not
a new type of a transaction. But what I'm trying to say
is, in some cases you could. Some people say if I take
this for מעשר ma'aser מוצאי שבת, motzai shabbos, it's like ערב שבת
erev shabbos it was already designated as the מעשר. ma'aser. That's more
ברירה breira that it shows retroactively this was this status. So here
the idea is if we're splitting it down the middle, we're trying
to say it wasn't like a transaction and a barter took place.
Well how could it be that no barter took place? It's only
no barter took place if the half that I took was always
the half that was coming to me. And that's a type of
a ברירה breira that it retroactively demonstrates that. So wait, let's just
read one more sentence to just get this idea done with. So
it says, that's what he says. הוא חלקו משעה ראשונה hu chelko
mish'at rishona
and in that case it's not like when they split up it's
not like they created a new entity, it's not a לקוח lakuach
problem, and when they rejoin it will reconstitute the estate. אמר רבי
יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan disagrees, he says
no, אפילו גדיים כנגד גדיים תיישים כנגד תיישים, afilu gedayim k'neged gedayim
t'yashim k'neged t'yashim, he disagrees with this ברירה breira idea or saying
that there could be times when it's not seen as something new
and not seen as transactional. He disagrees with that. Even if it
was split down the middle, you get half the kid goats, I
get half the kid goats, you get half the adult goats, I
get half the adult goats. כלקוח הן, k'lakuach hen, nevertheless when you
once you make the split, it's like you swapped your portion in
estate for somebody else's portion and it's considered a purchase. ופטורים מן
המעשר u'pturim min hama'aser and therefore you're exempt from מעשר ma'aser even
when you split it down the middle. כההיא דתנינן k'hu d'taninan like
we taught in the mishna, תמן, taman, לקוח lakuach if you purchase
something ושניתן לו במתנה v'shenitan lo b'matana if you receive a gift,
פטור ממעשר patur mima'aser you're exempt from מעשר. ma'aser. So again, the
difference here is that do we say that when we split the
estate, do we now become חייב chayav in מעשר ma'aser because now
it's personal ownership? Or do we say no, those animals that we
split are לקוח lakuach and those animals are exempt. So that's one
question, when we split it down the middle, is that לקוח lakuach
and exempt or is that personal ownership and חייב chayav or original
ownership I should say and חייב, chayav, or new ownership and exempt.
And a similar issue is when we reconstitute the estate, are we
creating something new called a partnership, which is exempt from מעשר בהמה
ma'aser behemah because of the idea of partnership, or are we reconstituting
the old of this entity of the estate and therefore it's obligated
מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behemah. Yes, question. Did they have wills in those
days? Did they have wills? They had something called מתנת שכיב מרע,
matnat shechiv mera, which is a deathbed bequest, which is sort of
like a will and they had things somewhat similar to that. In
that case though that wouldn't be considered a ירושה, yerusha, that wouldn't
be considered effectively a gift. And it would have the הלכה halacha
of ניתן לו במתנה, nitan lo b'matana, which is the other part
of this, but it would not be directly this case. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now, רבי חייא אמר רבי ירמיה
בעי, Rabbi Chiya amar Rabbi Yirmiyah ba'ei, so רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya
in the name of רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah asked the following question.
ולמה לית נן אמרין, v'lama lest nan amrin, why don't we say,
ולמה אין אנחנו אומרים, v'lama ein anachnu omrim, לית נן אמרין, lest
nan amrin, why don't we say. פעמים שהן חייבין בזה ובזה. pe'amim
shehen chayavin beze uveze. I can give you a scenario where based
on how they divided the estate, they could be obligated both in
the קולבון kalbon and the מעשר בהמה, ma'aser behemah, ופעמים שהן פטורים
מזה ומזה. upe'amim shehen peturim mize umize. And there are times they're
exempt from both. It's not one, it's not either, if it's this
way with one, it's the opposite with the other. I can give
you scenarios. What are the scenarios? היכא דמי? heicha dami? What would
be the scenarios? So we'll skip the parentheses. חלקו הנכסים ולא חלקו
בהמה. chalku hanekhasim velo chalku behemah. Which part of the estate are
you dividing? If you divide all of the property, let's say the
other property, the movable property, or certainly let's say the money of
the estate, and you don't divide the animals, so in that case
חייבין בזה ובזה. chayavin beze uveze. When you come to the question
of the שקל, shekel, you look at basically the most of the
sort of assets of the estate. So from that perspective, everybody's got
their portion, you're individuals, you each give. When you look at the
מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah question, you look at the question of who
owns the בהמות. behemos. So you didn't divide the בהמות. behemos. The
בהמות behemos are still owned by the estate. The בהמות behemos are
owned by the corporation, the other assets are owned privately. So for
מעשר בהמה, ma'aser behemah, you go by the corporation and it's חייב.
chayav. And for שקלים, shekalim, you go by the other assets and
it's also חייב chayav because everybody's an individual. Okay, so that's a
case of חייב בזה ובזה. chayav beze uveze. חלקו בהמה ולא חלקו
הנכסים. chalku behemah velo chalku hanekhasim. So then the reverse is also
true. Let's say you divided the בהמות. behemos. Those are owned privately.
זה לקוח. ze lakuach. לקוח, lakuach, right. And then maybe you reconstitute
it, or if you reconstitute it, it's שותפות, shutfus, but you divided
the בהמות, behemos, so those are either לקוח lakuach or net, or
if you rejoin now it's שותפות, shutfus, ולא חלקו הנכסים, velo chalku
hanekhasim, and but basically the assets of the estate are owned by
the estate. So in that case פטורים מזה ומזה. pturim mize umize.
You're פטור patur from מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah because once you divided
it, it has this לקוח lakuach status. But you're also exempt from
שקלים, shekalim, from the קולבון, kalbon, because it's one estate that has
really the assets, and that estate gives the שקלים, shekalim, maybe on
behalf of its members, but nevertheless, it's one entity and therefore it
is exempt from the קולבון. kalbon. You look at the major assets.
Now, of course, a fascinating question here that is not being asked
but being assumed, and I'll just put it on the table is:
why the heck should my status vis-a-vis שקל shekel go by the
estate I inherit? The שקל shekel isn't an obligation based, a tax
on the estate. The שקל shekel is my personal obligation. So even
if I had no money before my inheritance, my status vis-a-vis the
שקל shekel should be defined independently. And look, let's say I have
my own investments plus I share an estate that I inherit. Okay,
so why should my personal identity be defined in terms of I'm
part of a member of a household with my siblings, as opposed
to for 20 years I've been living as an independent person, I
don't like any of my siblings, I haven't spoken to them at
all, I'm totally an independent person, now we all inherit this estate,
and now when I come to pay my half שקל, shekel, you
say, 'Oh, you're not really an individual. You're a member of this
family defined by this estate.' Right? It's not so clear why we
would say that, right? So that's an interesting assumption here that once
these brothers or whoever it is inherit the estate, their identity versus
שקלים, shekalim, which is not based on assets, it's based on your
personal status, is somehow now all defined through the lens of this
estate that they inherited. Okay, so I just want, we'll have a
question somewhat like that coming up, but I want to point out
the irony of that, and that particularly the strangeness of that that's
brought out here by the question of: well, did you divide the
assets or divide the בהמה? behemah? For the בהמה, behemah, you're this
way; for the assets, you're that way. Why should your שקל shekel
go by assets and not go just by my personal status? Okay,
so let's see now as the גמרא Gemara continues. Wait, is that
פטור patur from the שקל shekel or פטור patur from the קולבון?
kalbon? No, the קולבון. kalbon. But I just meant my status for
the שקל shekel is seen this way. The נפקא מינה nafka mina
is do I pay a קולבון kalbon or not. Right, nobody's saying
I don't pay the שקל. shekel. Right. But in terms of considering,
now maybe the point is what assets are you using to pay
the שקל? shekel? If I pay the שקל shekel out of my
own pocket, so yes, thank you, Dov, that helps a lot. If
I pay the שקל shekel out of my own pocket and from
my own bank account, then of course I'm an individual and I
pay the קולבון. kalbon. But if the שקל shekel is being paid
for the members of the estate from the estate's bank account, then
for that we'll look at it as though the estate is paying
the שקל shekel for its members. Okay, so now let's take a
look. So it says it depends: are you dividing the animals, are
you dividing the bank accounts? So okay. אמר רבי מנא, amar Rabbi
Mana, הדא דאת אמר, hada de'at amar, sort of like היכא דמי,
heicha dami, when do we say this? We say this thing בשלא
היתה בהמה רוב bish-lo hayta behemah rov when the animals were not
the majority of the assets of the estate. אבל אם היתה בהמה
רוב aval im hayta behemah rov if the majority was the animals
were the majority of the assets, so even if you divided the
cash, if we all still hold the animals in, you know, undivided
partnership or undivided as the estate assets, so in that case, הן
הן עיקר נכסים hen hen iqar nechasim they will define the most
they will define the wealth, they will define the basic, you know,
sort of entity of the estate. So basically what we did is
we all divided up the cash and put that in our private
bank account, but we remained sort of undivided the ownership of all
of the animals that we inherited. So in that case when we
come to pay the שקל, sheqel, we wouldn't pay the קלבון kalbon
because we're still considered unified, the basic estate is still one entity
because that's still defined by the animals. Now this again is strange,
because the way we just explained it is whether I do or
don't pay the קלבון kalbon makes sense whether I'm giving the שקל
sheqel from the estate assets or from the, or from you know,
from my private assets. But presumably I'm not going in handing a
goat over for my שקל. sheqel. We talked about money changing, we
never thought about handing over actual like non-money. So again, why the
fact that we haven't divided the animals means that when we pay
our מחצית השקל machatzit hasheqel we're viewed as the money is coming
from the estate and we're coming as a unified entity rather than
as individuals, again, I don't know. It still seems, you know, it
is still something here that's very strange about that. Is this a
clarification or a קשיא? kashya? No, it's a clarification. It's a clarification,
היכי דמי. heichi dami. Okay, so again, that's why it seems like
it's not just a question where the check is being drawn from,
but that somehow if they're all partners in the estate it somehow
does define somewhat of their personal status. I agree with what Rebbe
Dov said, if you could say that the נפקא מינה nafqa mina
is where the money is coming from, coming from the estate, coming
from my personal, but then what's this idea that it gets defined
by the animals if the animals are the majority? Okay. So now
the גמרא Gemara continues. רבי אבין אמר רבי שמי בעא. Rabbi Avin
amar Rabbi Shimi ba'a. So רבי אבין Rabbi Avin in the name
of רבי שמי Rabbi Shimi asked. מפני שעשיתם כאדם אחד אצל מעשר
בהמה את פטור מן הקלבון? mipnei she-asitam ke-adam echad etzel ma'asar behemah
at patur min haqalbon? So this I understand is essentially there's a
question how to read this, but I'd like to read this as
the question that I just posed to you. Just because they are,
you've got to like the phrase like I said, a corporation is
a person. Just because they're like one person, just because the estate
makes them like one person, one entity for מעשר בהמה ma'asar behemah
purposes, how does it exempt them out of the קלבון? kalbon? Like,
who cares? The קלבון kalbon is a question of what you pay
for your שקל sheqel which is your private obligation. Who cares if
as far as the animals are concerned it's all owned by some
shared type of an estate. So he doesn't understand how this gets
you out of the קלבון. kalbon. אמר ליה, Amar leih, so who
he said back, I'm not clear who said back there, לא שאני
הוא שהוא נותן סלע אחת שלמה. lo shani hu she-hu noten sela
achat sheleimah. So the answer came back was, no, the reason you're
exempt in the case of the estate is, remember the הלכה halakhah
which is if I give a whole שקל sheqel for me and
for somebody else, if it's not a loan, if I'm basically giving
it for me and somebody else and for that other person it's
like a gift or something of that nature, then you just give
the whole שקל sheqel and you don't pay the קלבון. kalbon. So
saying really the reason that you're exempt for the קלבון kalbon is
not so much that you're one person. Okay, you're multiple people. But
again, assuming you're drawing the money for the שקל sheqel from the
estate, if the estate here is giving, let's say there are two
brothers who inherited this, האחים השותפין, ha-achim hashutfim, so assume it's two.
So there's two brothers and the estate gives one שקל, sheqel, so
it's not because we're saying you're conceptually one person for שקלים. sheqalim.
Fine, you're two people, but one שקל sheqel is being given for
two people. So therefore when one's given for multiple people all bundled
up together, you don't give the קלבון. kalbon. Actually, the משנה Mishnah
said you give one קלבון, kalbon, you don't give multiple קלבונות. kalbonot.
But the basic answer is, don't consider them one person, consider them
multiple people, but nevertheless it's one thing which is given for, you
know, one full שקל sheqel given for two people, that exempts them
from the קלבון. kalbon. So then the גמרא's Gemara question is then
it has nothing to do with them being heirs and being, inheriting
the estate. It's just a case of giving one thing for multiple
people. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, so let's take a
look. מעתה אפילו חלקו וחזרו ונשתתפו חייבין במעשר בהמה ופטורין מן הקלבון.
me-attah afilu chalqu ve-chazaru ve-nishtattfu chayavin be-ma'asar behemah u-feturin min haqalbon. If
that's true, so that, again the whole text is problematic. והתנינן חייב
בקלבון ופטור מן מעשר בהמה. ve-hateninan chayav baqalbon u-fatur min ma'asar behemah.
The way this text is switched is, אפילו חלקו וחזרו ונשתתפו afilu
chalqu ve-chazaru ve-nishtattfu they should be פטורין מן הקלבון. peturin min haqalbon.
Meaning according to you, it has nothing to do with them being
an estate. It has to do with the fact that you're giving
one coin for multiple people. So if that's true, even when they
split up and rejoined they should be exempt from the קלבון kalbon
because it's one coin for multiple people. So is it sort of,
again, is it sort of clear where we're going? Meaning we basically
said when you're this entity of corporation of an estate, then you're
חייב במעשר chayav b'ma'aser and you're פטור patur from, and you're פטור
patur from the קלבון. kalbon. So first the גמרא Gemara says, well,
what are you sort of shared in your entity? Are you sort
of, what are you an estate in, in the בהמה, behemah, in
the cash? What are you an estate in in terms of that?
But that then in a way highlighted the fact that it's not
totally about your identity, it's really about the assets. So that then
led to the question of, one minute, so who cares if from
these
assets you're part of a corporation? You're still an individual, so who
cares, you should always be חייב chayav in קלבון.
kalbon. And the answer at this stage is, you're right. The reason
you're פטור patur from קלבון kalbon is not because you're seen as
a part of a corporate entity. The reason you're exempt is because
one person is paying for multiple people. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so then why does the משנה Mishnah distinguish between whether the estate
divided or didn't divide or all those things? It shouldn't really have
anything to do with the concept of the estate according to that.
Okay, so let's see what the גמרא's Gemara's answer is. Again, we
have to do a little crossing out here in the text. Okay,
but now the two dots, רבי בא בשם אבא בר רב הונא,
Rabbi Ba b'shem Abba bar Rav Huna, שני אחים שירשו את אביהם
שני גיסים שירשו את חמיהם. sheni achim sheyarchu et avihem sheni gisim
sheyarchu et chamiehem. He basically says it doesn't matter whether it's two
brothers that inherited their father or two brothers-in-law that inherited their fathers-in-law.
Now what exactly that line means is very strange. First of all,
two brothers-in-law; two brothers can, two brothers-in-law don't inherit from their respective
father-in-laws and they certainly don't inherit the same type of an estate.
So what again what that line means is unclear. Some of the
מפרשים meforshim are basically saying that his answer is, you know what?
You're right. It has nothing to do with being an estate. Even
if it was, it's really not because of their status as an
estate, it's really because of their status that even if it was
not a ירושה, yerushah, it was like brothers-in-law who got different things
from their father-in-law. Nevertheless, if it's one gift for multiple people, you're
exempt. Again, it doesn't really answer the question because the משנה Mishnah
makes it clear that it's about the entity of the estate and
it matters that it was divided and reconstituted, where here we're basically
trying to push and say it's not about the estate. And therefore,
and if that last line means what it just did, it doesn't
matter, you're right, whether it's a real inheritance or not a real
inheritance, it's all the same הלכה, halachah, then we don't know why
it matters when you divide and reconstitute that it should be a
different הלכה. halachah. So, I wish I could make this גמרא Gemara
easier for all of you, but I'm doing the best I can.
Okay. I'm only, what? Thinking of corporations as business, everybody has to
give a half a shekel. Right. Well that's true, everybody is giving
a half a shekel, the question is whether you're giving a קלבון
kalbon or not. Okay, let's finish, okay, let's finish this. The last
line is a lot easier. לאיכן היו הקלבונות נופלים? le'eichan hayu hakalbonot
noplim? Where would, what would you do with these קלבונות? kalbonot? Okay,
which sort of also indicates their role. What would you do with
these little fees? So רבי מאיר אומר לשקלים, Rabbi Meir omer l'shekalim,
you'd add it to the שקלים shekalim funds, which very much fits
with רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that the purpose of the קלבון kalbon
is to round out the shekel. רבי אלעזר אומר לנדבה, Rabbi Eliezer
omer l'nedavah, you'd give it for different קרבנות korbanot to the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So שקלים shekalim go for regular קרבנות, korbanot, נדבה
nedavah are sort of free עולות olot that are brought on the
מזבח mizbe'ach when there's no business and you want the מזבח mizbe'ach
to look busy. So it's a type of a communal קרבן, korban,
but it's not the standard communal obligatory קרבן. korban. So it has
a related purpose, but not the same as the קרבן, korban, normal
קרבן. korban. רבי שמעון שזורי אומר רקועי זהב ציפוי לבית קדשי הקדשים,
Rabbi Shimon Shezuri omer riku'ei zahav tzipui l'beit kodshei hakodashim, which is
fascinating. Right, that's what they did with the fire pans of קורח,
Korach, they banged them into these covers for the, for the מזבח,
mizbe'ach, so here they say you make it a, you make it
like gold plating in the קדשי הקדשים. kodshei hakodashim. So why of
all things that? I have absolutely no idea. The last two make
a lot of sense, sort of are understandable where they're coming from.
בן עזאי אומר שולחניים היו נוטלים אותן בשכרן, Ben Azzai omer shulchanim
hayu notlim otan bischaran, you'd use it to pay for the money
changers, especially if you understand that it's basically a money changer fee.
ויש אומרים v'yesh omrim and some say להוצאת דרכים, l'hotza'at drachim, you
pay for the expenses of, not just general הוצאת דרכים, hotza'at drachim,
but it's understood as the travel expenses of getting of collecting the
half shekels. You have to pay to send people out and for
their travel expenses and all of that. So the last two are
basically the, this is really the difference that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says is to round out the shekel and the other approach is,
no, these are transaction fees and these are for operating expenses. So
whether it goes straight to the money changers, whether it goes to
general operating expenses for the whole process of collecting, at least there
we understand what to do with it. Okay, so that was quite
complicated, both the idea about why you pay multiple transaction fees, like
the idea that when you gave one and get back a half,
you pay two transaction fees. Some complicated ideas there. Also, we understand
the basic idea, it's a fascinating point as I said because הלכה
halachah doesn't really have much of an idea of a corporation. So
this concept of an estate and dividing and reconstituting, the difference between
a partnership and a corporation and for מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah you're
חייב chayav when it's one entity, but when it gets divided it's
either לקוח lakuach or when it gets reconstituted. Reconstituted it’s partnership whereas
by the קולבון Kalbon the more it’s one entity even if you
give multiple שקלים Shekalim if it’s seen as one entity you wouldn’t
give multiple קולבונות Kolbonot but then the גמרא Gemara at the end
seemed to challenge that. Why should our relationship to this money define
our status vis-a-vis our שקל? Shekel? So we had sort of said
maybe it’s where you’re drawing the funds from but that seemed to
be the question at the end where the גמרא Gemara seems to
actually step back from the idea that it has to do with
a partnership and say really anybody who’s giving one thing for multiple
people would you know would be exempt from the קולבון. Kalbon. Again
what that has to do with the partnership with the estate idea
is the challenge at the end where the answer was not very
clear. Okay. הדרן לך באחד באדר. Hadran Lach Be’echad Be’adar. Yes. The
big נפקא מינה Nafka Mina for creating an estate as opposed to
partnerships, right, is if you lose all your money with bankruptcy so
to speak and you had loans nobody’s חייב Chayav to repay. Exactly.
Exactly. But it also comes up more in ritual discussions like the
nature of ownership of a corporation and חמץ Chametz on פסח Pesach
and so on and how much are these things considered to be
like individual ownership or non-individual ownership and so on. But that’s true
in secular law. In Jewish law debts transfer from generation to generation.
Well only on only on property not as an abstract debt. Okay
anyway so let’s take a look at the next משנה. Mishna. Next
פרק. Perek. Okay. מצרפין שקלים לדרכונות. Metzarfin shekalim ledarkonot. Basically if you’re
doing local collections of שקלים Shekalim and then you’re going to send
them to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash rather than carrying a bag
full of these silver things you can exchange them for דרכונות Darkonot
which are gold coins which I believe are drachma, right? The Roman
drachma was that a gold coin? Anybody know Charlie? It's a drachma
was a gold coin. A gold coin? Okay I don’t know. Okay
you can take a look whether drachmas date to the time of
the Persian rule. Really? דרכון Darkon so it’s not a drachma? Okay
fine. Anyway whatever it is. Okay. מפני משא הדרך Mipnei masa haderech
in order to alleviate the weight of shipping those things to the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. כשם שהיו שופרות במקדש Keshem shehayu shofaros bamikdash
we’re going to find out in a later משנה Mishna that there
were different literally horns in the מקדש Mikdash they were basically like
boxes that you’d put your money in and they’d be shaped like
horns where it has a little slit in the top and a
big base at the bottom so you can’t stick your hand in
to take out anything. Okay but it collects a lot. So the
same way they had that in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash when
they were collecting in their local cities and villages they would also
put the money in these type of שופרות. Shofaros. Yes Charlie? Oh
there is another opinion that it is a Greek coin. It is
a Greek coin? Okay. כך היו שופרות במדינה Kach hayu shofaros bamdina
similarly they would have it in the מדינה Medina which some say
means in ירושלים Yerushalayim others say it just means in the throughout
the country. בני העיר ששלחו את שקליהם Bnei ha’ir sheshalchu es shiklehen
we’ll find out the significance of שופרות Shofaros later. Now בני העיר
ששלחו את שקליהם Bnei ha’ir sheshalchu es shiklehen ונגנבו או שאבדו. Venignevu
o she’avdu. They collected their entire village and they sent the money
off to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and on the way there
were bandits and it got stolen or got lost. So who’s liable?
Have they paid or not paid yet? So אם נתרמה התרומה Im
nitrema hatruma if the truma the allotment has been taken. I’ll tell
you what that means in a minute. So then נשבע. Nishba. I’ll
tell you what it means right now. Basically what we’re going to
find is the following: is that all the moneys that were collected
were put in these various שופרות Shofaros in the מקדש. Mikdash. And
then at three times in the year actually I think you had
this on the first day three times in the year they would
take from those collected moneys and take them out of those boxes
and not exactly clear what they would do with it they wouldn’t
buy all the animals for the next four months but maybe I
don’t know transfer to their bank account but they would remove the
actual moneys that were collected out of those boxes at three times
in the year and start putting them to use in terms of
buying the funds that they need. That’s called taking the תרומה Truma
like removing from the collected money and actually starting to use those
funds. Now let’s say here it is. It’s ראש חודש ניסן Rosh
Chodesh Nissan we have to start bringing new קרבנות. Korbanos. We’re going
to take some of this money out there and start using it
to buy new קרבנות. Korbanos. The only problem is and this you
had on the first דף Daf is that there’s a lot of
villages with 93% of precincts reporting there’s a lot of villages that
we don’t yet have their donation. Some of them it’s going to
take them six months to get us their donation and we have
to buy the new קרבנות Korbanos today. So what do we do?
So we take from the existing funds but we say the money
that we’re taking now out of the already collected funds because money
is fungible that’s seen to be drawing on all the funds that
have yet to be collected at this stage. מן הגבוי ומן העתיד
לגבות. Min hagavuy umin ha’asid ligvos. It’s drawing on the money that
was already collected and on the money that will in the future
be collected. So that act of taking the תרומה Truma if you’ve
got money your village has money on the way and here we
are in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and we’re taking this תרומה
Truma and we’re saying this counts for all the moneys that are
yet to be collected we’re implicitly basically saying saying that that money
on the road, we're already seeing it as if it's here, and
if we're drawing on it. So then in effect, you've now delivered
your, by the fact that we took from it with yours in
mind, was like you already delivered your money, and now if it
gets lost, it's our בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash money that's getting lost,
not your village's money that's getting lost. Okay, so that's the point...
right, exactly. Exactly. Okay, good good parallel. So it says, okay, אם
נתרמה תרומה, im nitrama truma, if the money's already been drawn on,
so נשבעים לגזברים, nishbayim lagizbarim, then the money effectively this stuff is
like it's already been received and the money that's lost is the
בית המקדש's Beis Hamikdash money that's been lost. So the people that
were carrying it are essentially the שומרים shomrim of the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. So they have to swear to the גזברים, gizbarim, to
the treasurers of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, that they weren't negligent,
and then the village would be exempt. We paid our money, it
was essentially effectively received, and then it got lost, we're exempt and
the carriers make take their oath. ואם לאו, ve'im lav, but if
the money has not yet been drawn on in the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, so effectively it has not yet been received, in that
case נשבעים לבני העיר, nishbayim livnei hair, the people that lost the
funds, the moneys were still of the people of the village and
they lost the money of the village. So they have to swear
to the villagers that they did not weren't negligent. ובני העיר, u'vnei
hair, and here's the big consequence, שוקלים תחתיהם, shoklim tachteichem, have to
give a whole other... like losing a blank check. Yeah, exactly. נמצאו
או שהחזירם הגנבים, nimtzu o shehachziram hagnanim, now if you then after
this happened, so the בני העיר bnei hair went through this whole
new levy, and everybody had to give again, and then you found
the old money, or the money got returned from the גנבים, gannavim,
they had a bout of conscience. אלו ואלו שקלים ואין עולין להם
לשנה הבאה. elu ve'elu shekalim ve'ein olin lahem leshana haba'ah. Of course,
the first thing you want to ask is can this new thing
that we collected count towards next year? And the answer is no.
It was given for this year, so they all go towards this
year's קרבנות. korbanot. Sorry guys, you don't get the money back. No,
it's הקדש. hekdesh. Yeah, cause once you give the שקל, shekel, and
that's going to be the next משנה, mishna, it's הקדש. hekdesh. So
once you've given it, it's הקדש. hekdesh. Now, if you just made
an announcement we're going to collect the money, and we haven't done
it yet, and then you find it, of course, so you're off
the hook. But if you actually gave it, you made it הקדש,
hekdesh, and now you have the old one is הקדש hekdesh as
well. Now why didn't you say it's הקדש בטעות? hekdesh b'ta'us? Okay,
but this is the assumption of the... the problem with that of
course is it would it would make people feel resentment. No kidding.
No kidding. I'm sure they're going to feel resentment even if the
old stuff wasn't found. I have to give again? I just gave.
You know? So let let the שלוחים shluchim be the ones who
give. Exactly. Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara
that leads into another... All right, anyway, so, okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says, ועשו אותן מרגליות, ve'asu otan margaliyot, why do we only
transfer them into gold coins? Why not if we want to make
it easy to transport, you know, convert it into into diamonds, convert
it into pearls? שמא תזיל המרגליות ונמצא הקדש מפסיד, shema tazil hamargaliyot
venimtsa hekdesh mafsid, because those have more of a... those more fluctuate
in value than currency. Currency is relatively stable in value. So those,
if those go down in value, הקדש hekdesh will lose out. כי
דתנינן תמן, ki detanynan tamman, like we taught over there, in בכורות,
Bechoros, וכולן נפדין בכסף ובשוה כסף, vechulan nifdin bechesef uveshaveh chesef, a
whole range of things can be redeemed, not only on money, but
on any type of valuable. חוץ משקלים, chutz mishkalim, with the exception
of שקלים, shekalim, שקלים shekalim you cannot redeem on objects, you can
only redeem on money, and for the reason that we are saying
right now. ואין פודין בכלים, ve'ein podin bechelim, you do not redeem
with vessels. Now, of course, that's obvious. If the only thing you
can redeem with is money, of course you can't redeem with vessels.
But anyway, ואמר רבי שמואל בר רב יצחק, ve'amar Rabbi Shmuel bar
Rav Yitzchak, שמא יזילו הכלים ונמצא הקדש מפסיד. shema yazilu hakeilim venimtsa
hekdesh mafsid. We're afraid that if you redeem on vessels, that the
vessels will go down in value and הקדש hekdesh will lose out.
ובהכא נמי, u'vhacha nami, here too, שמא תזיל המרגליות ונמצא הקדש מפסיד.
shema tazil hamargaliyot venimtsa hekdesh mafsid. If you did it on some
pearls or, you know, valuable stones, then it would then they would
go down in value and הקדש hekdesh would lose out. What's not
clear what's not clear is what is the case, it sounds like
the case that you don't redeem on כלים keilim is different from
the שקלים shekalim case. But it's not so clear what case that
is. Because either the either the הלכה halacha is that you can
redeem on anything for certain types of things that you can redeem,
or you can only redeem
on
coins.
This makes it sound like there's another area of הלכה halacha where
you can redeem on anything but כלים, keilim, which is like not
not true. So again, where this line where they're using כלים keilim
as an example for, where that applied originally is not clear. But
the basic answer is clear. We teach also in משנה בכורות, Mishna
Bechoros, yes, you cannot redeem שקלים shekalim on anything other than coins,
because everything else has fluctuating value, and therefore that is too big
of a concern of a loss to הקדש. hekdesh. Yes, coins also
have fluctuating value. Yes, I was waiting for somebody to say that.
Yes, I was thinking when did this occur that they became exchangeable.
Well, but the question... The question is, the question is, is that,
so yes, coins of different metals I assume have fluctuating, but in
areas of fixed currency, I'm sure you know this much better than
I do, right? When you have—there was actually a fixed ratio, I
assume set by the government, you know that like x number of
silver coins equals one gold coin. Now the reality is is that
the—that the value of gold to silver could fluctuate. And have. And
has. So how—how that was handled by the, you know, but nevertheless
the reality was—And handled very poorly by the government. Let me say
that. Okay. But the reality was—but the reality was was that there
was a fixed ratio. So when you convert your silver coins to
gold coins, there's not going to be any loss because even if
the value of gold fluctuates vis-à-vis silver, the government, whatever, recognizes that
fixed ratio of those coins and that's what—Very good, yes. And so
I was wondering something else: when did the gold actually become an
investment in itself that it was barred at different values? Yeah, so
the גמרא Gemara does talk about buying gold as—like gold bars, not
just gold coins, but again, I don't, you know, some of that
comes up in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia where there's a whole question
about what's considered coins and what's considered property, whether gold coins might
be considered property and silver be considered the standard of what's considered
money. And there's all these other halachic—There's a מחלוקת machlokes there about
what—what is the real metal—Exactly. Alright, let's keep on going. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this: מתניסה בתקלין חדתין אבל בתקלין עתיקין
לא בדא. Matnisa bitaklin chadashin, aval bitaklin atikin lo bada. Our משנה
Mishnah is about new shekels but not old shekels. What does that
mean? It means old shekels is you're still paying last year's shekel.
You didn't get around to paying last year's shekel. So when do
we say basically that—just let me check one thing here—yes, that you
would basically collect the money in the villages and then ship it
off, that's every year's new collection would be done in the village.
If you basically are back taxes, are in arrears, then and you
want to now give your old—last year's shekel, then you have to
go to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Then you cannot give it
in your village. Okay, so when we do the village collecting, that's
only for this year's shekel. ותני כן, V'sani ken, we taught in
a ברייתא, Braisa, עתיקין במקדש ואין עתיקין במדינה. atikin bamikdash v'ein atikin
b'medinah. In the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash they would collect the old
shekels but not in the מדינה. medinah. There it would only be
for this year. Okay, now this idea of taking an oath if
it got stolen. So the גמרא Gemara says, מתניתין בשומר חינם. Matnisin
b'shomer chinam. Our משנה Mishnah that you take an oath is that
you're a שומר חינם. shomer chinam. אבל בשומר שכר לא בדא. Aval
b'shomer sachar lo bada. But if it's a שומר שכר, shomer sachar,
this would not be the case because a שומר שכר shomer sachar
is חייב בגניבה ואבידה. chayav b'gneivah v'aveidah. It's not taking an oath,
you'd actually have to pay. אמר רבי אבא, Amar Rabi Abba, says
רבי אבא, Rabi Abba, ואפילו תימא בשומר שכר, v'afilu teima b'shomer sachar,
even by שומר שכר, shomer sachar, נגנבו
בלסטין מזויין אבדו כמי שטבעה ספינתו בים. nigneivu b'listin mizuyin, avdu k'mi
shetavah sfinato bayam. There are scenarios of גניבה ואבידה gneivah v'aveidah which
are scenarios of אונס.
oness. Normally גניבה ואבידה gneivah v'aveidah is in the space between full
negligence and completely out of your hand, between פשיעה pshiah and אונס.
oness. And that's the space that a שומר שכר, shomer sachar, a
paid guardian, is obligated in. But there are types of גניבה gneivah
that are a complete אונס, oness, there's nothing you could have done.
You were attacked by armed robbers. There's nothing you could have done.
It wasn't that you didn't lock it up well enough, it wasn't
that you didn't try to defend, you had no choice, you were
attacked by armed robbers. That's a גניבה gneivah that's an אונס oness
that even a שומר שכר shomer sachar is exempt from. There's an
אבידה, aveidah, so if you lost it, where did I put it,
it slipped out of my pocket, that's obviously that's pretty close to
פשיעה. pshiah. Okay, but it could be an אבידה aveidah like—like you
know—lost not in the sense of I don't know where it is,
but lost in the sense of, you know, I no longer was
able to get it. You know, I was going ahead and—you know,
it says like I was shipping it on a boat and the
boat sank. Hurricane Sandy. Hurricane Sandy, that's a loss which is an
אונס. oness. So it says it could be, we could have scenarios
of the משנה Mishnah of even a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. But
it is true the standard scenario would be one of being a
שומר חינם shomer chinam and being exempt because you're a שומר חינם.
shomer chinam. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רבי
יוסי בר רבי סימון, Amar Rabi Yosi bar Rabi Simon, אתיא כמאן
דאמר תורמין על הגבוי ועל העתיד לגבות. asya k'man d'amar tormin al
hagavui v'al ha'asid ligvos. This is what I said. The reason once
they take תרומה trumah it's considered like it's been received is the
opinion that when they took the moneys, they were taking it not
only on the moneys collected but on the things that were going
to be collected as well. ברם כמאן דאמר אין תורמין לא על
הגבוי ועל העתיד לגבות לא בדא. Bram k'man d'amar ein tormin lo
al hagavui v'al ha'asid ligvos lo bada. But according to the position
that they did not take it on stuff that was collected and
that was on its way, it was only taken from the moneys
that were actually in hand, so according to that approach, even once
they drew on those funds, until the money has been received, it
hasn't been received. So actually, that's a much better position from the
village's perspective, right? You would want it to be considered not received
until you actually get it out of your hands and are free
from any liability. Okay, so—oh no, I'm sorry. The opposite. I'm sorry,
I'm sorry, the opposite is true. You want it to be considered
received, I'm sorry, as soon as possible so if anything goes wrong,
your village has already— much more challenging place. תורמין על הגבוי Tormin
ala hagibuy means incur expenses for whatever is required in the מקדש.
Mikdash. No, תורמין Tormin means when you take it out. They had
where all the moneys were put when they came to the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Then they would draw three times during the year
from all of those
שקל shekel and basically sort of like deposit them into the הקדש's
Hekdesh's bank account and start writing checks from that bank account. תורמין
Tormin is that act of taking it out. הגבוי Agibuy is money
that's been collected, and עתיד לגבות atid ligvot is the money that
is yet to be collected. Right, right, but תורמין Tormin is when
they transfer into the bank account and the מקדש Mikdash and start
writing checks. Exactly. Right, though there were no checks. Right. Okay. בני
העיר ששולחין שקליהן, Bnei hair shesholchin shkalim, so now we take to
the idea of the שבועה. shvua. אמר רבי אלעזר דרבי שמעון היא,
Amar Rabbi Elozar de'Rabbi Shimon hi, this idea that you would take
an oath when something happened to the שקל shekel only goes according
to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
because we got a
little problem, you don't take oaths on הקדש. Hekdesh. So what are
you doing taking a שבועה shvua about what happened to the הקדש?
Hekdesh? So he says that's going according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
רבי שמעון אומר קדשים שהוא חייב באחריותן כנכסיו הן, Rabbi Shimon omer
kodshim she'hu chayav be'achrayusan ke'nechasav hen, right, if you are חייב chayav
in the liability, then even if the object is הקדש Hekdesh they're
treated as non-הקדש Hekdesh because you are primarily the one who is
liable for them, so they're like your normal property. So basically the
village is going to be liable if the money gets lost. So
this שקל shekel is considered to be like normal village funds because
from the monetary perspective the village will lose out. And therefore the
שומרים shomrim or the shippers will have to take an oath to
the villagers because it's not like an oath on הקדש; Hekdesh; from
the villagers' perspective, it's their money. It's not הקדש Hekdesh and therefore
they will have to take an oath. So that works. But according
to others, why are they taking an oath? This money is הקדש.
Hekdesh. So if it's not considered to be standard like as if
it's the villagers' money, why is there an oath? אמר רבי יוחנן
דברי הכל היא, Amar Rabbi Yochanan divrei hakol hi, no, it's not
just רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, משום שבועת תקנה. mishum shevuas takana. Basically
it's דרבנן, derabbanan, it's a תקנה. takana. You don't, yes, biblically you
don't take an oath on this, but here, this if you basically
say, oh sorry your שקל shekel got lost, right, so A, nobody's
going to be happy, and B, it's a disrespect to הקדש Hekdesh
that you basically can just say oops and there's going to be
no consequence. So there has to be a שבועה shvua in order
to show some respect in order to make you more careful and
in order that there's respect to the הקדש. Hekdesh. But it's דרבנן.
derabbanan. על דעתיה דרבי יוחנן, Al daitei de'Rabbi Yochanan, according to the
position of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, ניחא נשבעים לגזברים, nicha nishba'im legizbarim,
we understand the scenario that when it's considered already collected they have
to take an oath to the treasurers, גזברים. gizbarim. ואם לאו נשבעים
לבני העיר, Ve'im lav nishba'im livnei hair, and in the other case
when it hasn't been the תרומה teruma yet, they take the oath
to the villagers. ובני העיר שוקלין אחרים תחתיהן, U'bnei hair shoklin acheirim
tachteihen, and the people have to give others. ועשו משום שבועת תקנה,
Ve'asu mishum shevuas takana, that's all because of this תקנה. takana. אלא
רבי אלעזר, Ella Rabbi Elozar, but according to רבי אלעזר Rabbi Eleazar
who says that it's considered owned by the בני העיר bnei hair
because if they lose it it's out of their pocket and therefore
it's not considered הקדש, Hekdesh, so נשבעים לבני העיר הדה היא דרבי
שמעון, nishba'im livnei hair hadah hi de'Rabbi Shimon, the scenario where they
swear to the villagers, yes that works with רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
because it's like the villagers' money and it's not הקדש. Hekdesh. נשבעים
לגזברים, Nishba'im legizbarim, but to swear to the גזברים, gizbarim, right, when
it's considered already collected, גזברים מה עבידתייהו, gizbarin ma avidasaihu, what are
the גזברים gizbarim doing? It's not the גזברים's gizbarim's money, it's הקדש's
Hekdesh's money. So in the second case of the משנה mishna where
הקדש Hekdesh loses out, in the first case where הקדש Hekdesh loses
out and they swear to הקדש, Hekdesh, you've got a problem. That's
a real oath on הקדש. Hekdesh. Not only is the money קדוש,
kadosh, it's owned by הקדש. Hekdesh. So where would be, there would
be no normal place here for a normal שבועה. shvua. Is that
clear? Meaning if you say it's not a תקנה, takana, you take
a שבועה shvua if the person losing is a lay person, then
even if the money is הקדש Hekdesh you take a שבועה shvua
according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon without a תקנה. takana. But in
the case where you're taking this oath to the גזברים, gizbarim, so
the money is הקדש, Hekdesh, the owners are הקדש, Hekdesh, there's no
reason other than a תקנה takana to take the שבועה shvua in
that. One minute, so that's the גמרא's Gemara's question. So the גמרא,
Gemara, so now it says and you wanted to know where there's
a בבלי Bavli part, so let's look at the גמרא's Gemara's answer.
So the גמרא's Gemara's question is why are you swearing to the
גזברים gizbarim in that case? גמרא Gemara says no, נשבעים לבני העיר
במעמד גזברים. nishba'im livnei hair bema'amad gizbarim. You swear to the villagers
in the presence of the גזברים. gizbarim. Why are you swearing to
the villagers? They're exempt from their obligation. כי היכי דלא ליחשדוניה, Ki
heichi delo lechasdenhu, so you shouldn't be suspected, you the deliverer. אי
נמי דלא נשוו ליה פושעים, Inami delo nashu lei poshim, they shouldn't
treat you as negligent. So according to this it sounds like you're
going to swear to the villagers not because their money is lost,
they don't actually have to pay any more in this case, but
because but they don't want to say, "You guys, you're good-for-nothing, you
were negligent on the job, or maybe you pocketed the money, you
embezzled the money." So even though the villagers aren't losing out of
their funds, because it already was considered belonging to הקדש, Hekdesh, you
have to swear to them so they're not angry at you. Okay,
and when it says גזבר, Gizbar, it just means that the גזברים
Gizbarim were present. One minute. Now, the problem with this answer is,
is that it doesn't really fit here because, you know, well, I
mean it could, like many דחק dachak answers in the גמרא, Gemara,
it's saying it's not what you thought, there's no oath to the,
to the what-do-you-call-it, to the גזברים, Gizbarim, you know, it's only to
the villagers. But also this שבועה shvua then, that you shouldn't be
angry at me or suspect me is not a traditional שבועה, shvua,
even this שבועה shvua is a Rabbinic שבועה. shvua. So anyway, it
could make sense and that is the answer. But what some of
the מפרשים Meforshim point out is, is that this line נשבעין לבני
העיר במעמד גזברים nishba'in livnei ha'ir bema'amad gizbarim is something that the
בבלי Bavli says when dealing with this משנה Mishna in a different
discussion for a different reason and it's an answer to a different
question in the בבלי. Bavli. And they say that this whole line
here was incorrectly grafted from the בבלי Bavli into this סוגיא. sugya.
And actually, if you look at the כתב יד ליידן, Ktav Yad
Leiden, this whole answer of נשבעין לבני העיר במעמד גזברים nishba'in livnei
ha'ir bema'amad gizbarim isn't in the כתב יד ליידן. Ktav Yad Leiden.
So this would be an example of something that has a graft
from a בבלי Bavli that doesn't really fit so well here. You
could make it fit, yeah, the משנה Mishna doesn't mean it, it
means something else for a totally different reason. But again, it most
likely is just something imported from the בבלי. Bavli. One minute. I
just want to finish this point. אף על פי שקבלו בני העיר
לשלם אין הקדש יוצא בלא שבועה. af al pi shekiblu bnei ha'ir
leshallem ein hekdesh yotze belo shvua. And even though, now here's another
הלכה. halacha. Let's say, this is a new point, let's say the
villagers say, "Look, you know what, our money was lost after you
did the תרומה. truma. We feel bad about that. We're going to
give a new donation. We're going to actually regive a שקל shekel
and we're going to get our guys who delivered it off from
having to make a שבועה." shvua. What do you care הקדש? Hekdesh?
We're just going to give the money again. Okay, so the הלכה
halacha is no, you still have to make a שבועה shvua because
basically this is the תקנה. takana. The תקנה takana is you should
never be seen as being negligent with הקדש's Hekdesh funds. So even
if at the end of the day you're going to reimburse הקדש,
Hekdesh, it won't get you out of the שבועה. shvua. We insist
in part of this תקנה takana that you don't get, that you
don't get off of the שבועה. shvua. I just want to, I
have to hold the questions, I just want to get to the,
to the next משנה, Mishna, we should at least finish that. We'll
just go for two more minutes. הפריש שקלו ואבד. hifrish shkalo ve'avad.
Now let's say a case somebody on a, not a village, a
privately I separated off my שקל shekel and now I can't find
my שקל. shekel. רבי יוחנן אמר חייב אחריותו. Rabbi Yochanan amar chayav
achrayuso. Okay, you have to owe us another שקל. shekel. Why not?
Duh. Okay, but listen to this. עד שימסרנה לגזבר ad sheyimserena lagizbar
until you hand it over to the גזבר, Gizbar, or maybe until
they do the תרומה, truma, okay? Question, would it matter if you're
doing it at an individual level as opposed to a village level?
But now here's the real חידוש. chiddush. רבי שמעון בן לקיש אומר
הקדש ברשות גבוה בכל מקום שהיא. Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish omer hekdesh
birshut gavoha bechol makom shehi. He says, "What do you mean lost?
This money belongs to the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, belongs to God,
wherever it is, it's God's." Okay, God knows where it is. Now
that's of course this funny idea, which is the difference between the
sort of קדושה kedusha of the object and God in the abstract
owner, and הקדש Hekdesh as a real-world institution like the Vatican's bank,
you know, is huge as a real-world institution. So the, the bank
of the הקדש Hekdesh doesn't know where it is, but God knows
where it is. So you're not חייב. chayav. I gave my שקל,
shekel, wherever it is, that's where it is. Okay, so implications for
the entire סוגיא sugya that we did. So that's what the גמרא
Gemara has to ask. So why don't the people that are carrying
the money say, "Wherever it is, that's where it is? The גנבים,
gannavim, they have it. Go get it from them." So let's take
a look. So okay, מתניתא, matnita, our משנה, Mishna, פליגי על ריש
לקיש, pligi al Reish Lakish, נשבעין לבני העיר. nishba'in livnei ha'ir. Why
should they, why would you ever have to, why make a שבועה
shvua to the הקדש? Hekdesh? Fine, because you don't want הקדש Hekdesh
to be, you know, you want to show you weren't irresponsible and
you do that even if they're getting their money. But why would
the בני העיר bnei ha'ir have to give a second time? The
בני העיר bnei ha'ir could just say, "Wherever the money is, it
belongs to הקדש." Hekdesh. So לא היא משום תקנה. lo hi mishum
takana. So it says, you know what, you're right. According to, so
one minute, oh no, so they switched the גרסא girsa or to
something like לא היא משום תקנה lo hi mishum takana as opposed
to שבועת תקנה. shvuat takana. They say, you're right, that's a תקנה
takana as well. But ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is saying is, מעיקר
הדין me'ikar hadin the city people would never have to pay again
because whoever has the money, the גנבים, gannavim, it's lost, we, we
sanctified the money, we were יוצא חיוב, yotze chiyuv, God knows where
it is. The only reason they have to reimburse, pay a second
time is the same way the שבועה shvua was a תקנה, takana,
this is a תקנה. takana. So it's a fascinating idea. Technically speaking,
they would never have to pay again because it's wherever it is,
it belongs to God. I just want to finish to the משנה.
Mishna. תני, tani, הראשונים. harishonim. Now let's say you had to give
a second time because it got stolen and then the old stuff
was found. What do you do with the double funds? Where do
they go to? Do they all go to this year's קרבנות? korbanos?
What do you do with them? So he taught in the... ברייתא
*Braisa*, הראשונים *Harishonim*, the first of the funds, נופלים לתקלין חדתין *noflim
letachlin chadashin*, are used for the new שקל *shekel* for the new
קרבנות *Korbanos*. השניים *Hashniyim*, the second of the funds, נופלים לתקלין עתיקין
*noflim letachlin atikin*, go to back, you know, payments and whatever we
do with old שקלים *shkalim*, with funds that were collected for old
debts, we would do with the second of the funds. Now, which
is the first and which is the second? Okay, so that's the
question. אלו הם ראשונים ואלו הם שניים *elu heim rishonim ve'elu heim
shniyim*, which is the first and which is the second in the
case where they were stolen, you gave again, and then they were
found or returned? רבי פנחס בי רבי חייה, רבי אבא אמרי *Rabbi
Pinchas bei Rabbi Chiya, Rabbi Abba amari*. So, a debate of these
two אמוראים *Amoraim*. חד אמר *chad amar*, אלו ששלחו בני העיר תחילה
*elu sheshalchu bnei ha'ir techila*, that's the, that would seem the obvious
thing, the ones that you originally gave that got lost and then
found again or stolen and returned, those are the first funds, and
those go for the new קרבנות *Korbanos*. The ones you had to
give the second time because they got lost, that's considered, that will
go for old שקל *shekel*. וחד אמר *vechad amar*, the other says
a more interesting answer. אלו שהגיעו לידי הגזברים תחילה *elu shehigi'u liydei
hagizbarim techila*. Now you got two sets of funds, and you got
to get them both to the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, so the
first ones to get to the גזברים *gizbarim*, those are for your
new שקלים *shkalim*. The second funds, which you were forced to give,
that'll go to old funds and to whatever we do with old
שקלים *shkalim*, we will do with them. All right, so.